Frederick A. Masse Jr. Papers MS043
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Frederick A. Masse Jr. Papers
circa 1960 -- 1986
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Masse, Frederick Arthur, Jr.
MS043
3.6 Linear Feet 3 boxes
This collection contains the papers of Frederick A. Masse, Jr., Tufts alumnus.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Series 2 is the gift of Woburn Public Library, 2016, accession MS-2017-035.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Frederick A. Masse Jr. papers, and Ethiopian materials.
Biographical / Historical
Frederick Arthur Masse, Jr. (circa 1931- April 25, 1987) was born in Woburn, Massachusetts, the son of Frederick A. and Mildred A. (Grimes) Masse and one of five children: Shirley, Francis, David, and Myrna. He received his B.A. from Tufts in English (A 1952). He served later on in the U. S. Foreign Service in Ethiopia in the early 1960s. During his life, Masse taught in Ethiopia, Iran, Sudan, Great Britain and Newport, RI. Masse was an English teacher for the Ministry of Fine Arts and Education in Addis Ababa 1958-1961 and 1963-1966. During this time he also served as tutor to two of Emperor Hailie Selassie's grandchildren. In 1962-1963 Masse taught high school in Khartoum. He served as a visiting lecturer in English as a Foreign Language at Georgetown University in the summer of 1975. From 1976 to circa 1978 he taught for the Imperial Iranian Navy. He also taught as English instructor at the Washington Technical Institute. After retiring as a teacher, he lived in Miami, Florida. Masse married Margaret Page (Margaret M. Massé), a Howard University graduate, in November 1970, but they were divorced by 1978.
Related Materials
Please consult the "Ethiopian Materials Collection" in Special Collections at Michigan State University for additional papers by Frederick Massé.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains Frederick A. Masse's personal correspondence and an autobiographical text, "Royal Bastards and Freed Slaves Volume 1," as well as materials documenting Masse's experiences working for the US Foreign Service in Ethiopia in the 1960s and 1970s, including scrapbooks, photographs, sketchbooks, journals, correspondence, publications, and memorabilia such as drawings, a wooden Ethiopian cross, and human hair.
Content Warning
This finding aid contains language that may be offensive or outdated. Because such language is in titles or direct transcription of materials, it has not been changed. Keeping this language intact provides the most accurate depiction of the creators' intent, and can potentially tell us important things about bigotry and bias on the part of the creators, or in a particular historical context. It can also preserve terms formerly applied by a group to self-identify that have since fallen out of common usage.
Masse, Frederick A., Jr.; Ethiopia--Politics and government; Alumni collections
- Frederick A. Masse, Jr. papers, 1978 -- 1986; MS043.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains an autobiographical text covering part of Frederick A. Masse's time in Ethiopia (1960-1961). It also includes photocopies of his personal correspondence which he bound in volumes. The series contains volumes 2-5. Volumes, 1, 6 and 7 are missing.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Autobiographical Trilogy on living in Ethiopia, "Royal Bastards and Freed Slaves Volume 1", 1980; MS043.001.001.00013 (Box Shared 133)
    Text consists of journal entries from 1960-61 covering the coup d'etat and earthquakes, but Masse organized and copyrighted the material in 1980.
  - Correspondence, Book 2, 1978 -- 1982; MS043.001.001.00014 (Box Shared 133)
  - Correspondence, Book 3, 1982 -- 1983; MS043.001.001.00015 (Box Shared 133)
  - Correspondence, Book 4, 1983 -- 1984; MS043.001.001.00016 (Box Shared 133)
  - Correspondence, Book 5, 1984 -- 1985; MS043.001.001.00017 (Box Shared 133)
  - Collection Correspondence, 1986; MS043.001.001.00018 (Box Shared 133)
- Ethiopian materials, circa 1960 -- 1979; MS043.002; 2.4 Linear Feet One record carton and four 12x16" flat boxes
  This series documents Tufts alum Frederick A. Masse Jr.'s experiences living in Ethiopia in the 1960s and 1970s as an employee of the US Foreign Service. It comprises scrapbooks, photograph albums and loose photographs, sketchbooks, appointment books and calendars, journals, correspondence, publications, and memorabilia. Included are drawings, a wooden Ethiopian cross, a framed painting, and human hair.
  This series is arranged by format.
  One diary restricted at request of donor.
  - Correspondence, 1975 -- 1978; MS043.002.002.000001 (Box 5-7; 2-6, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbooks, 1958 -- 1968; MS043.002.002.000002 (Box 5-7; 2-6, Folder 2-3)
  - Memorabilia, circa 1960 -- 1979; MS043.002.002.000003 (Box 5-7; 2-6, Folder 4-8)
  - Journals and diaries, 1964 -- 1980; MS043.002.002.000004 (Box 5-7; 2-6, Folder 9-18)
    Folder 11 restricted by request of donor.
  - Photographs, circa 1960 -- 1979; MS043.002.002.000005 (Box 5-7; 2-6, Folder 19-20)
  - Publications and teaching materials, circa 1970 -- 1979; MS043.002.002.000006 (Box 5-7; 2-6, Folder 21-27)
  - Photograph album, circa 1960 -- 1979; MS043.002.003 (Box 5-7; 2-6)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1968 -- 1975; MS043.002.004.000001 (Box 5-7; 2-6)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1975 -- 1980; MS043.002.004.000002 (Box 5-7; 2-6)
  - Photograph album, circa 1960 -- 1979; MS043.002.005.000001 (Box 5-7; 2-6)
  - Painting of Ethiopian man, circa 1960 -- 1979; MS043.002.005.000002 (Box 5-7; 2-6)
  - Ethiopian wooden cross, circa 1960 -- 1979; MS043.002.006.000002 (Box 5-7; 2-6)
  - Photograph album, circa 1960 -- 1979; MS043.002.006.000001 (Box 5-7; 2-6)
  - Hair sample, circa 1960 -- 1979; MS043.002.006.000003 (Box 5-7; 2-6)